<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ardhi.treaty.00016">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Anglo Portuguese Treaty 1890</title>
<principal n="Muchiri, Nganga">Nganga Muchiri</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Howells, Phillip H." xml:id="phh">Phillip H. Howells</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2021</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">ardhi.treaty.00016</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Anglo Portuguese Treaty 1890</title>
<title level="m"></title>
<publisher></publisher>
<biblScope></biblScope>
<date when="1890">1890</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
<language ident="po">Portuguese</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>  
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Treaty</term>
</keywords>     
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/95738652/#Victoria,_Queen_of_Great_Britain,_1819-1901">Victoria, Queen of Great Britain, 1819 1901</term>
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/71400758/#Carlos_I,_Rei_de_Portugal,_1863-1908">Carlos I of Portugal, King of Portugal from 1889–1908</term>
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/44350506/#Salisbury,_Robert_Cecil,_Marquess_of,_1830-1903">Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Marquess of, 1830-1903</term>
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/98560184/#Freitas,_Augusto_C%C3%A9sar_Barjona_de,_1834-1900">August César Barjona de Freitas</term>
</keywords>
<keywords n="treatydate">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="geonames" n="places">
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/2635167/united-kingdom-of-great-britain-and-northern-ireland.html">Great Britain</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/2264397/portuguese-republic.html">Portugal</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1027917/ruvuma-river.html">River Rovuma</term>
<term>River M'Sinje</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/924329/lake-nyasa.html">Lake Nyassa</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1048465/lake-chiuta.html">Lake Chiuta</term>
<term>River Chilwa</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1027846/ruo-river.html">River Ruo</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1048833/shire-river.html">River Shire</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1026014/tete.html">Tété</term>
<term>Kabra-bassa Rapids</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1024693/zumbo.html">Zumbo</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/876728/zambezi-river.html">Zambesi</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/886397/mazoe.html">River Mazoe</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/1027190/save.html">River Save</term>
<term>River Masheke</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/909226/lunte.html">Lunte</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/953987/south-africa.html">South Africa</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/934841/eswatini.html">Swaziland</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/945829/lusutfu.html">River Maputa</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1040651/baia-de-maputo.html">Delagoa Bay</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/964569/pongolo.html">River Pongola</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/877177/katima-mulilo-rapids.html">Katima Rapids</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/912983/kapompo.html">Kabompo</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/2800866/brussels.html">Brussels</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/2950159/berlin.html">Berlin</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/933840/chobe-district.html">Chobe</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1028495/pungwe.html">Pungwé Bay</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1085597/limpopo.html">Limpopo</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000083">
<persName>Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Marquess of, 1830-1903</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000084">
<persName>August César Barjona de Freitas</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-11" who="#phh"></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="x"/>
<div2>
<p>HER Maje.sty the Queen of the United
Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland,
Empress of India, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c., and His
Most Faithful Majestj' tlie King of Portugal
and the Algarves, &amp;c., &amp;c, &amp;c,, being
animated with the desire to draw closer the
tie.s of friendship which unite the two
nations, and to settle by common accord
certain matters relative to their respective
spheres of influence in Africa, have determined to conclude a Convention to that
effect, and have named as their respective
Plenipotentiaries—that is to say :—</p>
<p>Her Majesty the Queen of the United
Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland,
Empress of India, the Right Honourable
Robert Arthur Talbot Gascoyne Cecil,
Marquis of Salisbury, Earl of Salisbury,
Viscount Cranborne, Baron Cecil, Peer of
the United Kingdom, Knight of the Most
Noble Order of the Garter, Member of Her
Majesty’s Most Honourable Privy Council,
Her Maje.sty’s Principal Secretary of State
for Foreign Affairs, &amp;c.;</p>
<p>And His Most Faithful Majesty the King
of Portugal and Hie Algarves, August Cesar
Barjona de Freitas, Councillor of His
Majesty and of‘ State, Peer of the Realm,
Minister and Honorary Secretary of State,
Grand Cross of Christ, aiivl Grand Cross
of several foreign Orders, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of
His Most Faithful Majesty at the Court of
Her Britannic Majesty, &amp;c.;</p>
<p>Who, having communicated to each other
their respective full powers found in good
and due form, have agreed upon the following Articles:—</p>
<ab>ARTICLE I.</ab>
<p>Great Britain agrees to recognize, as within
the dominion of Portugal in East Africa, the
territories bounded—</p>
<p>1. To the north by a line which follows
the course of the River Rovuma from its
niouth up to the confluence of the River
M’Sinje, and thence westerly along the
parallel of latitude to the shore of Lake
Nyassa.</p>
<p>2. To the west by a line which, starting
from the above-mentioned frontier on Lake
Nyassa, follows the eastern shore of the lake
southwards as far as the parallel of latitude
13° 30' south; thence it runs in a south-easterly direction to the eastern shore of
Lake Chiuta, which it follows. Thence in
a direct line to the eastern shore of Lake
Chilwa, or Shirwa, which it follows to its
south-easternmost point; thence in a direct
line to the easternmost affluent of the River
Ruo, and thence follows that affluent, and
subsequently, the centre of the channel of
the Ruo to its confluence with the River
Shird. From thence it runs in a direct line
to a point half-way between Tété and the
Kabra-bassa Rapids.</p>
<p>The Settlement of Zumbo, with a radius
on the northern bank of 10 English miles,
remains under the dominion of Portugal,
but shall not, without the previous consent
of Great Britain, be transferred to any other
Power.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE II.</ab>
<p>To the south of the Zambesi, the territories within the Portuguese sphere of
influence are bounded by a line which,
starting from a point opposite the western
extremity of the lO-mile radius of Zumbo,
runs directly southwards as far as the 16th
parallel ofsouth latitude, follows that parallel
to its intersection with the 31st degree of
east longitude (Greenwich , thence running
eastward direct to the point where the River
Mazoe is intersected oy the 33rd degree of
east longitude; it follows that degree southwards to its intersection by the 18° 30'
parallel of south latitude; runs along that
parallel westward to the affluent of the River
Save or Sabi, which is called the River
Masheke; follows that affluent, and afterwards the centre of the main channel of the
Save, to the confluence of the Lunte, whence
it strikes direct to the north-eastern point
of the frontier of the.Soath African Republic,
and, follows the eastern frontier of the
Republic, and the frontier of Swaziland, to
the River Maputa.</p>
<p>Portugal engages not to cede her territories to the south of the Zambesi to any
other Power without the previous consent
of Great Britain.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE III.</ab>
<p>Great Britain engages not to make any
objection to the extension of the sphere of
influence of Portugal, south of Delagoa Bay,
as far as a line following the parallel of the
confluence of the River Pongola with the
River Maputa to the sea-coast.</p>
<p>Portugal engages that the territory of
which the limits are defined in this Article
shall not, without the consent of Great
Britain, be transferred to any other Power.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE IV.</ab>
<p>It is agreed that the western line of division separating the British from the Portuguese sphere of influence in Central Africa
shall follow the centre of the channel of the
Upper Zambesi, starting from the Katima
Rapids up to the junction with that river of
the River Kabompo, and thence up the
centre of the channel of the Kabompo.</p>
<p>The country hereby recognized as Portuguese shall not, without the consent of Great
Britain, be transferred to any other Power.</p>
<p>It is understood on both sides that nothing
in this Article shall affect the existing rights
of any other State. Subject to this reservation, Great Britain will not oppose the
extension of the Portuguese sphere of influence beyond the abovementioned limits.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE V.</ab>
<p>Portugal agrees to recognize, as within
the sphere of influence of Great Britain on
the north of the Zambesi, the territories
extending from the line described in the
preceding Article to Lake Nyassa, including
the islands in that lake south of parallel
11° 30', and to the line described in
Article I, with the exception of Zumbo and
a radius of 10 English miles round it.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE VI</ab>
<p>Portugal agrees to recognize, as within
the sphere of influence of Great Britain to
the south of the Zambesi, the territories
bounded on the east and north-east by the
line described in Article II.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE VII.</ab>
<p>All the lines of demarcation traced in
Articles I to VI shall be subject to rectification by Agreement between the two Powers,
in accordance with local requirements.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE VIII.</ab>
<p>The two Powers engage that neither
will interfere with any sphere of influence
assigned to the other by Articles I to VI.
One Power will not in the sphere of the
other make acquisitions, conclude Treaties,
or accept sovereign rights or Protectorates.</p>
<p>It is understood that no Companies nor
individuals subject to one Power can exercise
sovereign rights in a sphere assigned to the
other, except with the assent of the latter.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE IX.</ab>
<p>Trading and mineral Concessions, and
rights to real property, held by Companies
or individuals, subjects of one Power, shall,
if their validity is duly established, be recognized in the sphere of the other Power. It
is understood that Concessions must be
worked in accordance with local Laws and
Regulations.</p>
<p>If a difference of opinion shall arise
between the two Governments as to the
validity of the Concession, or as to the
equitable character or suitability of the
above-mentioned local Laws and Regulations, it shall be settled by the arbitration
of a jurisconsult of a neutral nationality.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE X.</ab>
<p>In all territories in Africa belonging to or
under the influence of either Power, missionaries of both countries shall have full
protection. Religious toleration and freedom
for all forms of divine worship and religious
teaching are guaranteed.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE XI.</ab>
<p>The two Powers engage that, in their
respective spheres, as defined in Articles I
to VI, trade shall enjoy complete freedom;
the navigation of the lakes, rivers, and
canals, and of the ports on those waters,
shall be free to both flags; and no differential treatment shall be permitted as
regards transport or coasting-trade; goods,
of whatever origin, shall be subject to no
dues except those, not differential in their
incidence, which may be levied for objects
directly connected with the administration,
or the suppression of the Slave Trade under
the provisions of the Act of the Brussels
ponference, or to meet expenditure in the
interest of trade; no transit-dues shall be
permitted, and no monopoly or favour in
matters of triiclc can be granted. The subjects of either Power will be at liberty to
settle freely in the territories within the
respective spheres.</p>
<p>Portugal reserves her right to exclude
from the operation of the free zone provisions of the Act of Berlin, and from the
provisions of the preceding paragraph, her
ports on the East Coast. She also reserves
the right to exclude from the operation of
the provisions of the preceding paragraph
her ports on the West Coast.</p>
<p>She engages, however, not to charge
transit-dues exceeding a maximum of 3 per
cent, OQ goods passing in transit inwards or
outwards between the coast and the British
sphere of inhuence, either by land or water.
These dues shall in no case have a differential character, and shall not exceed the
customs dues levied on the same goods at
the above-mentioned ports.</p>
<p>It is understood that, under the terms of
this Article, there shall be freedom for the
passage of subjects and goods of both
Powers across the Zambesi, and through the
districts adjoining the river for the purpose
of such passage, along its whole course,
without hindrance of any description and
without payment of transit-dues.</p>
<p>It is further understood that within a
zone of 20 English miles on the north bank
of the Zambesi Portugal shall have the right
to construct roads, railways, bridges, and
telegraph-lines across the territories reserved
to British influence on the north of the
Zambesi. Both Powers shall have the same
right within a zone of 10 English miles on
the south of the Zambesi between Tété and
the confluence or the Chobe, and within a
zone of the same dimensions running from
the north-east of the British sphere south of
the Zambesi to the above-mentioned zone.
The two Powers shall have the power, in
these zones, of acquiring, on reasonable conditions, the land necessary for such objects,
and shall receive all other requisite facilities.
They shall also be allowed facilities for the
construction on the river, between the above-named limits, of piers and landing-places for
the purpose of trade or navigation. All
materials for the construction of roads, railways, bridges, and telegraph-lines shall be
admitted free of charge.</p>
<p>Differences of opinion between the two
Governments as to the execution of their
respective obligations, incurred in accordance
with the provisions of the preceding paragraph, shall be referred to the arbitration
of two experts, one of whom shall be chosen
on behalf of each Power, who shall select an
Umpire, whose decision, in case of difference
between the Arbitrators, shall be final. If
the two experts cannot agree upon the
choice of an Umpire, this Umpire shall be
selected by a neutral Power.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE XII.</ab>
<p>The navigation of the Zarabesi and Shiré,
without excepting any of their branches and
outlets, shall be entirely free for the ships of
all nations.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE XIII.</ab>
<p>Merchant-ships of the two Powers shall
in the Zambesi, its branches and outlets,
have equal freedom of navigation, whether
with cargo or ballast, for the transportation
of goods and passengers. In the exercise
of this navigation the subjects and flags of
both Powers shall be treated, in all circumstances, on a footing of perfect equality, not
only for the direct navigation from ihe open
sea to the inland ports of the Zambesi, and
<hi rend="italic">vice versa</hi>, but for the great and small
coasting trade, and for boat trade on the
course of the river. Consequently, on all
the course and mouths of the Zambesi there
will be no differential treatment of the subjects of the two Powers; and no exclusive
privilege of navigation will be conceded by
either to Companies, Corporations, or private
persons.</p>
<p>I'he navigation of the Zambesi shall not
be subject to any restriction or obligation
based merely on the fact of navigation. It
shall not be exposed to any obligation in
regard to landing-station or depôt, or for
breaking bulk, or for compulsory entry into
port. In all the extent of the Zambesi the
ships and goods in process of transit on the
river shall be submitted to no transit dues,
whatever their starting-place or destination.
No maritime or river toll shall be levied
based on the sole fact of navigation, nor any
tax on goods on board of ships. There
shall only be collected taxes or duties which
shall be an equivalent for services rendered
to navigation itself. The Tariff of these
taxes or duties shall not warrant any differential treatment.</p>
<p>The affluents of the Zambesi shall be in
all respects subject to the same rules as the
river of which they are tributaries.</p>
<p>The roads, paths, railways, or lateral
canals which may be constructed with the
special object of obviating the innavigability
or correcting the imperfections of the river
route on certain sections of the course of
the Zambesi, its affluents, branches, and
outlets, shall be considered, in their quality
of means of communication, as dependencies
of this river, and as equally open to the
traffic of both Powers. And, as on the river
itself, so there shall be collected on these
roads, railways, and canals only tolls calculated on the cost of construction, maintenance, and management, and on the profits
due to the promoters. As regards the
Tariff of these tolls, strangers and the
natives of the respective territories shall be
treated on a footing of perfect equality.</p>
<p>Portugal undertakes to apply the principles of freedom of navigation enunciated in
this Article on so much of the waters of the
Zambesi, its affluents, branches, and outlets,
as are or may be under her sovereignty,
protection, or influence. The rules which
she may establish for the safety and control
of navigation shall be drawn up in a way to
facilitate, as far as possible, the circulation
of merchant-ships.</p>
<p>Great Britain accepts, under the same
reservations, and in identical terms, the
obligations undertaken in the preceding
Articles in respect of so much ofthe waters
of the Zambesi, its affluents, branches, and
outlets, as are or may be under her sovereignty, protection, or influence.</p>
<p>Any questions arising out of the provisions of this Article shall be referred to a
Joint Commission, and, in case of disagreement, to arbitration.</p>
<p>Another system for the administration
and control of the Zambesi may be substituted for the above arrangements by
common consent of the Riverain Powers.</p>
<p>Portugal will, on application from Great
Britain, grant to a Company a lease for
100 years of 10 acres at the mouth of the
Chindé, for purposes of transhipment. The
ground so leased shall not in ariv case be
fortified.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE XIV.</ab>
<p>In the interest of both Powers, Portugal
agrees to grant absolute freedom of passage
between the British sphere of influence and
Pungwd Bay for merchandize of every
description, and to give the necessary facilities for the improvement of the means of
communication. She undertakes to construct a railway to serve this region within
a jperiod fixed by surveys which shall be
completed with the least possible delay.
An engineer named by the British Government
shall take part in these surveys, which
shall commence within a period of four
months from the signature of this Convention. In case these conditions should not
be precisely carried out, Portugal will grant
to a Joint Company under the control of
Portuguese and British Directors, and with
seats in Lisbon and London, with the least
possible delay, a Concession for the construction of a Railway, with all requisite
facilities for the acquisition of land, cutting
timber, and free importation and supply of
materials and labour.</p>
<p>It is understood that no dues shall be
levied at the port of entry or exit on goods
in transit exceeding the maximum of 3 per
cent. under the conditions stipulated in
Article XI.</p>
<p>It is further understood that the same
provision as to goods in transit applies to
the Limpopo, the Save, and all other navigable rivers flowing to the coast of the
Portuguese spheres in East or West Africa,
with the exception of the Zambesi.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE XV.</ab>
<p>Great Britain and Portugal engage to
facilitate telegraphic communication in their
respective spheres.</p>
<p>The stipulations contained in Article XIV
as regards the construction of a railway
from Pungwé Bay to the interior shall be
applicable in all respects to the construction
of a telegraph-line for communication between the coast and the British sphere south
of the Zambesi. Questions as to the points
of departure and termination of the line,
and as to other details, if not arranged by
common consent shall be submitted to the
arbitration of experts under the prescribed
conditions.</p>
<p>Portugal engages to maintain telegraphic
service between the coast and the River
Ruo, which shall be open to the use of the
subjects of the two Powers without any
differential treatment.</p>
<p>Great Britain and Portugal engage to give
every facility for the connection of telegraphic lines constructed in their respective
spheres.</p>
<p>Details in respect to such connection, and
in respect to questions relating to the settlement of through tariffs and other charges,
shall, if not settled by common consent, be
referred to the arbitration of experts under
the prescribed conditions.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE XVI.</ab>
<p>All differences not specifically mentioned
in the preceding Articles which may arise
between the two Governments with regard
to this Convention shall be submitted to
arbitration.</p>
<ab>ARTICLE XVII.</ab>
<p>The present Convention shall be ratified,
and the ratifications shall be exchanged at
London as soon as possible.</p>
<p>In witness whereof the respective Plenipotentiaries have signed the present Convention, and have affixed thereto the seal of
their arms.</p>
<p>Done in duplicate at London, the twentieth
day of August, in the year of Our Lord one
thousand eight hundred and ninety.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="signatures">
<signed>(L.S.) SALISBURY.</signed>
<signed>(L.S.) BARJONA DE FREITAS.</signed>
</div2>
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>