<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ardhi.treaty.00006">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Sierra Leone Treaty of 1819</title>
<principal n="Muchiri, Nganga">Nganga Muchiri</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Howells, Phillip H." xml:id="phh"></name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2020</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">ardhi.treaty.00006</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m">The African-British Long Eighteenth Century</title>
<title level="a">Sierra Leone Treaty of 1819</title>
<publisher></publisher>
<biblScope></biblScope>
<date when="2009">2009</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>  
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Treaty</term>
</keywords>     
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords n="treatydate">
<term>1807</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="geonames" n="places">
<term>Mar Porto</term>
<term>Ro Bompe</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/2403846">Sierra Leone</term>
<term>Bunch River</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
  <term>Timmanies</term>
</keywords>  
</textClass>

<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000045">
<persName>MacCarthy, Charles</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000046">
<persName>Konko</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000033">
<persName>Firama</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000047">
<persName>Naingbanna</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000048">
<persName>Bandio, Moimadoo</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000049">
<persName>Kattena</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-09" who="#phh">encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="ardhi.treaty.00006.001"/>
<div2>
<head>SIERRA LEONE TREATY OF 1819</head>
<ab><hi rend="italic">Agreement for Mar Porto &amp; Ro Bompe-renamed called Waterloo &amp;
Hastings, Sierra Leone</hi></ab>
<ab>Convention between His Excellency Lieut. Colonel Charles MacCarthy, Captain 
General and Governor Chief in and over the Colony of Sierra Leone and
its Dependencies Vice Admiral of the same &amp;c. &amp;c. and Commander in Chief
of His Majesty's Forces on the West Coast of Africa on the part of His Majesty
the King of Great Britain and Ireland, and Pa Loudon commonly known by the
name and style of Ka Conko, and his Chieftains, Headmen &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</ab>
<p>His Excellency the Captain General and Governor in Chief being anxious
to maintain the happy union and harmony which have for several years past
<pb/>
<fw><hi rend="italic">Appendix of Treaties</hi>                                             171</fw>
subsisted between the Colony of Sierra Leone and the Timmanies, wishing to
strengthen and renew the former Treaties made by his Predecessors with the
King and Chieftains, to prevent all misunderstanding which might arise from
misconception as to the proper limits and boundaries of the Colony, the rights
and titles of British subjects under the Authority of the Governor and Council
hereafter to former Establishments on such parts of the left bank of the Bunch
River as are at present unoccupied by British Subjects, and Pa Loudon commonly 
called Ka Conko and his Chieftains, Headmen and Gentlemen, being
animated with the same sentiment, have for the benefit of all parties concerned
agreed as follows</p>
<p>The said Pa Loudon Commonly called Ka Conko his Chieftains, Headmen
and Gentlemen have for themselves and their Successors, ceded, transferred,
and given to his said Excellency Governor McCarthy as Governor for the time
being, for the use and on the behalf of His Majesty, the King of the United
Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and his successors, the full, entire,
free, and unlimited possession and Sovereignly of the Territory and lands
commonly known under the name Mar Porto and Ro Bompe situated on the
Banks of the Bunch River and extends from, to, with all right and title to the
Navigation of the same River; water on the Riverlet situated on the left side
of the aforesaid.</p>
<p>The extent and limits of the aforementioned Lands of Mar Porto and Ro Bumpe
shall be duly established in the presence and with the consent of Pa Loudon
commonly called Ka Conko or a Person or Persons duly authorized by him to
that affect and no alterations in said limits shall hereafter under any pretence
or plea be permitted under the authority or Sanction of His said Excellency the
Governor or his Successor without ihe concurrences of the said Pa Loudon or
his Successor, it being fully understood that within the extent of those limits
only British subjects shall have right to occupy lands in the district.</p>
<p>In consideration of which transfer of Land, His said Excellency the Captain
General and Governor in Chief for himself and Successors as the Governor of
Sierra Leone for the time being, on the part and on the behalf of His Britannic
Majesty engages, promises and agrees to pay yearly and every year to the said
Pa Loudon commonly called Ka Conko, or to such person as may succeed him
or be appointed or authorized to receive the same, the Sum of Fifty Bars in
lieu of all other claims or demands of whatever nature or description/the yearly
Rent of a hundred Bars to Kin Farima excepted which shall continue as here-
to-for/And His Excellency solemnly promises for himself and his successors
for the time being on the part of His Britannic Majesty, not to disturb or molest
any of the native Inhabitants who may now occupy any Town, House or Fait,
whither the extent of the limits of the place aforementioned.</p>

<pb facs="ardhi.treaty.00006.002"/>
<fw>172                                             <hi rend="italic">Appendix of Treaties</hi></fw>
<p>It is further agreed by the contracting parties that the Year Rent of Fifty Bars
shall become due and payable on the fourth day of June in each year, the same
to commence from the fourth of June next and payable on the same day of the
year One-Thousand Eight hundred and Twenty, and to consist of the following
articles which are to be taken at rate here agreed upon, and not liable to any
alteration.</p>
<p>Lastly in fault of due on regular payment of the yearly Rent above agreed upon,
the present Treaty shall be considered as null and void.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="signatures">
<p>In Witness whereof the said Contracting parties at Freetown in the Colony of
Sierra Leone on the Twenty-Fifth day of May One-thousand eight hundred and
nineteen, have hereunto set their hand and seals in presence of the subscribing
Witnesses.</p>
<signed>Lt C. MacCarthy</signed>
<signed>"Pa Loudon + Konko"</signed>
<signed>"Pa Naingbanna"</signed>
<signed>"Moimadoo Bandio"</signed>
<signed>"Pa Kattena"</signed>
</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
