<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ardhi.treaty.00027">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Beira Customs Regulations May 1891</title>
<principal n="Muchiri, Nganga">Nganga Muchiri</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Howells, Phillip H." xml:id="phh">Phillip H. Howells</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2021</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">ardhi.treaty.00027</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Beira Customs Regulations May 1891</title>
<title level="m"></title>
<publisher></publisher>
<biblScope></biblScope>
<date when="1891">1891</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>  
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Treaty</term>
</keywords>     
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Joaquin Machado</term>
</keywords>
<keywords n="treatydate">
<term>1891</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="geonames" n="places">
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1052373/beira.html">Beira</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1028495/pungwe.html">Pungwe River</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/2264397/portuguese-republic.html">Portugal</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1040947/manica-province.html">Manica</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1036973/republic-of-mozambique.html">Mozambique</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="pers.0000115">
<persName>Joaquin Machado</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-12" who="#phh">encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="x"/>
<div2>
<ab><hi rend="italic">Provisional Regulations for carrying out the Provisions of Article 1 of the Decree, having
force of law, of the 18th November, 1890.</hi></ab>
<ab>(Translation.)</ab>
<p>ARTICLE I. All merchandize disembarked at the port of Beira, and going up the
Pungwe in order to reach the territories beyond the Portuguese sphere of influence as
fixed by Article 4 of the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> of the 14th November, 1890, shall pay 3 per
cent, <hi rend="italic">ad valorem</hi> only, in accordance with the provisions of Article 1 of the Decree,
having force of law, of the 18th November, 1890.</p>
<p>Art. II. As long as the condition of the country does not allow more practical and
liberal measures, the owner, agent, or broker of the merchandize passing through
Portuguese territory in transit shall observe the following Regulations:—</p>
<p>(a.) He shall state on the transit bill, made out in the required form, the quantity
and quality of the goods which he intends to clear, and shall then clear them.</p>
<p>(b.) He shall present to the Head of the Revenue Office of Manica the transit way
bill delivered to him by the Custom-house at Beira, and shall submit the goods to the
inspection of merchandize which will take place at the Revenue Office in question.</p>
<p>(c.) He shall deposit, to the order of the Director of the Custom-house at Beira, a
sum equal to 12 per cent. of the value of the goods to be cleared, or shall present the
guarantees of two suitable persons living in Beira, who shall make themselves responsible 
for the payment of such sum when demanded by the Treasury.</p>
<p>(d.) The sum deposited shall be repaid to the person who deposited it, or to his
lawful representative, or, as the case may be, the guarantors shall be relieved of the
guarantee, on presentation of the certificate issued after the inspection of the merchandize
at the Revenue Office of Manica.</p>
<p>(e.) If this certificate is not presented within a period of six months, the deposit
shall be called in as a receipt to the Treasury, or, as the case may be, the guarantors
shall be compelled to pay in the amount for which they are responsible.</p>
<p>(f.) If at the inspection at the Revenue Office of Manica any of the merchandize is
found to be missing, the official in charge of the Office shall make a statement of the
goods missing, and of the duty leviable thereon, according to the Import Tariff in force
in the province; and the amount of such duties shall be called in by the Custom-house
at Beira from the deposit or from the guarantors liable.</p>
<p>(g). If more than the right-amount of merchandize is found, the agent shall at the
Revenue Office of Manica clear the goods that are over for exportation, paying the
duties in Table (B) of the Tariff in force where the merchandize is the produce or
manufacture of the Province (of Mozambique); and the duties in Table (A), increased by
100 per cent. as a fine, where they have been imported from without that province, and
should consequently have been passed through the Customs at Beira.</p>
<p>Art. 3. The importation of alcohol, gin, gunpowder, arms and munitions of war of
all kinds, except under written order issued by tlie superior authorities of the province
or by their representatives, is prohibited.</p>
<p>Art. 4. The Customs will verify summarily all merchandize declared for transit, and
in so doing: will be guided mainly by the bills of landing; a rigorous examination wil
only be made where there are reasons for suspecting fraud in these papers.</p>
<p>Art. 5. The Customs will prepare the (transit) way bill in triplicate of all
merchandize declared for transit; one original will be placed in the archives of the
Department, another will be handed to the owner or agent of the goods, who will
present it to the Revenue Office at Manica, and the third will be sent officially to the
Mead of the Revenue Office in question.</p>
<p>Art 6. All merchandize found in Portuguese territory without a transit way bill or
other legal document shall be considered as having evaded the duties, and as such may
be seized by any Portuguese authority, who shall send them to the nearest Revenue
Office for the proceedings enjoined by the Regulations in force.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="signatures">
<signed>(Signed) J. MACHADO, <hi rend="italic">Governor-General.
Office of the Governor-General of the Province of Mozambique,
Personal Department of the Governor-General,
Staff Office, Beira, May</hi> 18,1891.</signed>
</div2>
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>