<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ardhi.treaty.00026">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Beira Customs Regulations April 1891</title>
<principal n="Muchiri, Nganga">Nganga Muchiri</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Howells, Phillip H." xml:id="phh">Phillip H. Howells</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2021</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">ardhi.treaty.00026</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Beira Customs Regulations April 1891</title>
<title level="m"></title>
<publisher></publisher>
<biblScope></biblScope>
<date when="1891">1891</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>  
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Treaty</term>
</keywords>     
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Joaquin Machado</term>
</keywords>
<keywords n="treatydate">
<term>1891</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="geonames" n="places">
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1052373/beira.html">Beira</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1028495/pungwe.html">Pungwe River</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/2264397/portuguese-republic.html">Portugal</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1040947/manica-province.html">Manica</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="pers.0000115">
<persName>Joaquin Machado</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-11" who="#phh">encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="x"/>
<div2>
<ab><hi rend="italic">Provisional Regulations referred to in the Decree, Article 1, which came into force on the
18th November</hi>, 1890.</ab>
<p>ARTICLE 1. All merchandize discharged at the port of Beira for transhipment via
the Pungwe River to the territories beyond the Portuguese sphere of influence, as set down
in Article 4 of the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> dated the I4th November, 1890, have to pay only
3 per cent, <hi rend="italic">ad valorem</hi> duty, in compliance with the rules of the Decree dated the
18th November, 1890.</p>
<p>Art. 2. While the state of the country does not permit to adopt more practicable
and more liberal measures, the owners, agents, or conductors of goods which are passing
through Portuguese territories in transit have to observe the following rules:—</p>
<p>(a.) To render a written statement of the quantity and quality of the goods they
wish to dispatch in transit, and to clear the same.</p>
<p>(5.) To hand to the fiscal official in Manica a list of the goods for transit, which list
he received from the Customs at Beira, and to submit to an examination of the goods in
his charge.</p>
<p>(c.) To deposit at the Customs at Beira the difference between the 3 per cent, and
the amount of duty which would be payable if those goods had been imported to be
consumed within Portuguese territory.</p>
<p>(d.) This deposit will be refunded to the depositor or his legal representative against
his handing a certificate of the examination made by the fiscal official at Manica within
three months.</p>
<p>(e.) Should the said certificate not have been rendered within a period of three months,
the deposit will be collected by the Government.</p>
<p>(f.) In case the examination made by the fiscal official at Manica should give a minus
of the goods, the official will make a note of the difference and the corresponding duty
according to the dispatch. The amount of these duties will be collected by the Customs at
Beira out of the respective deposit.</p>
<p>(g.) Should there be a surplus of the goods, the conductor will be obliged to make a
dispatch for the exportation before the fiscal official against paying duty according to the
Tariff (Table B).</p>
<p>Art. 3. It is prohibited to import powder, guns, or any ammunition of war without a
written order of the superior authority of the province or his representative.</p>
<p>Art. 4. The Customs have a right summarily to examine the goods for transit, being
guided as much as possible by the ship’s manifest; they only can make a vigorous examination 
should there be motives for suspicion.</p>
<p>Art. 5. The Customs will make out a list in triplicate of the goods for transit, one
copy to remain in the archives of the Department; the second will be handed over to the
owner or agent of the goods, to be delivered to the fiscal official at Manica; the third copy
will be sent officially to the said official.</p>
<p>Art. 6. All goods met with on Portuguese territories without a transit list, or any legal
document, will be considered as smuggled goods, and will be seized as such by any Portuguese 
authority, who will send the same to the next fiscal official, to be proceeded with
according to the Regulations in force.</p>
<p>Given at head-quarters, Beira, the 17th April, 1891.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="signatures">
<signed>(Signed) JOAQUIN MACHADO,
<hi rend="italic">Governor-General</hi>.</signed>
</div2>
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>