<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FILENAME">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Germany Portugal Treaty 1886</title>
<principal n="Muchiri, Nganga">Nganga Muchiri</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Howells, Phillip H." xml:id="phh">Phillip H. Howells</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2020</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project"></idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Germany Portugal Treaty 1886</title>
<title level="m"></title>
<publisher></publisher>
<biblScope></biblScope>
<date when="1886">1886</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
<language ident="ge">German</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>  
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Treaty</term>
</keywords>     
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/121595990/#Lu%C3%ADs_I_de_Portugal_Rei_de_Portugal_e_Algarves_(1861%E2%80%931889)">Luís I de Portugal Rei de Portugal e Algarves (1861–1889)</term>
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/43148190/#Wilhelm_I._Deutsches_Reich,_Kaiser_1797-1888">Wilhelm I. Deutsches Reich, Kaiser 1797-1888</term>
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/23548025/#Gomes,_Henrique_de_Barros,_1843-1898.">Henrique de Barros Gomes</term>
<term>Richard von Schmidthals</term>
</keywords>
<keywords n="treatydate">
<term>1886</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="geonames" n="places">
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2264397/portuguese-republic.html">Portgual</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2271989/algarve.html">Algarve</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2921044/federal-republic-of-germany.html">Germany</term>
<term>Southwest Africa</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/3355854/rio-cunene.html">River Kunene</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/3348297/humbe.html">Humbe</term>
<term>Serra Canna</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/876337/cuando-cubango.html">Kubango</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/877352/andara.html">Andara</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/3350299/catima.html">Catima</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/876728/zambezi-river.html">Zambesi</term>
<term>Southeast Africa</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/1027917/ruvuma-river.html">River Rovuma</term>
<term>River M'sinje</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/924329/lake-nyasa.html">Lake Nyassa</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/3351879/republic-of-angola.html">Angola</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/1036973/republic-of-mozambique.html">Mozambique</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2267057/lisbon.html">Lisbon</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>  
</textClass>

<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="pers.000057">
<persName>Henrique de Barros Gomes</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="pers.000058">
<persName>Richard von Schmidthals</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021" who="#phh">Initial encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="x"/>
<div2>
<ab>(Translation.)</ab>
<p>THE Government of His Majesty the King of Portugal and the Algarves, and the
Government of His Majesty the German Emperor, animated by the same desire to draw
more closely the existing friendly relations between Portugal and Germany, and to gain
a firm and secure basis for peaceful co-operation in the opening out of Africa to civilization
and commerce, have resolved to establish certain boundaries, within which each of
the two Powers shall keep their freedom of action for their colonizing activity.</p>
<p>For this purpose the Undersigned, Henrique de Barros Gomes, State Councillor of
His Most Faithful Majesiy, and his Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and Councillor
Richard von Schmidthals, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of His
Majesty the Emperor, have, in accordance with their full powers, agreed upon the
following Articles;—</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE I.</head>
<p>The boundary-line which shall separate the Portuguese and German possessions in
South-West Africa follows the course of the River Kunene. from its mouth to the
waterfalls which are formed to the south of Humbe by the Kunene breaking through the
Serra Canna. From this point the line runs along the parallel of latitude to the Kubango,
then along the course of that stream to the village of Andara, which is to remain in the
German sphere of influence, and from thence due east to the rapids of Catima, on the
Zambesi.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE II.</head>
<p>The boundary-line winch shall separate the Portuguese from the German possessions
in South-East Africa follows the course of the River Rovuma from its mouth to the point
where the Biver M’sinje joins the Bovoma and mns to the westward on the pallet of
latitude to the shores of Lake Nyassa.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE III.</head>
<p>The Government of His Majesty the German Emperor recognize the right of His
Majesty the King of Portugal to those territories which lie between the Portuguese
possessions of Angola and Mozambique, without prejudice of any rights other Powers
may have previously acquired of exercising their sovereign and civilizing influence, and
bind themselves in consequence of this recognition not to make any acquisitions of
territory, nor accept any Protectorates within these provinces, nor to oppose the
extension of Portuguese influence.</p>
<p>The Government of His Majesty the King of Portugal and the Algarves undertake
the same obligation with regard to the territories given over to the German sphere of
influence by Articles I and II of this Agreement.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE IV.</head>
<p>Portuguese subjects in the German possessions of Africa, and subjects of the
German Empire in the Portuguese possessions, shall enjoy the same rights and treatment,
with regard to the protection of their persons and property, with regard to the acquisition
and transfer of personal and real property, and with regard to the exercise of their trade,
as the subjects of the State which exercises the sovereign or protecting rights.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE V.</head>
<p>The Portuguese and Imperial Governments reserve the right of concluding further
Agreements to facilitate commerce and navigation, as well as to regulate the frontier
traffic in the African possessions on both sides.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="signatures">
<signed>(L.S.) BARROS GOMES.</signed>
<signed>(L.S.) SCHMIDTHALS.</signed>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ADDITIONAL ARTICLE.</head>
<p>This Agreement will come into force and become binding for both Powers as soon
as it is agreed to by the Portuguese Cortes, and published in the official prints of both
countnes.</p>
<p>Done in duplicate at Lisbon on the 30th December, 1886.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="signatures">
<signed>(L.S.) BARROS GOMES.</signed>
<signed>(L.S.) SCHMIDTHALS.</signed>
</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>