<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ardhi.treaty.00007">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title></title>
<principal n="Muchiri, Nganga">Nganga Muchiri</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Howells, Phillip H." xml:id="phh">Phillip H. Howells</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2021</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">ardhi.treaty.00007</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">France Portugal Treaty 1886</title>
<title level="m"></title>
<publisher></publisher>
<biblScope></biblScope>
<date when="1886">1886</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>  
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Treaty</term>
</keywords>     
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/74230588/#Corvo,_Andrade,_1824-1890">Joao de Andrade Corvo</term>
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/24021254/#Bocage,_Carlos_Roma_du,_1853-1918">Carlos Roma du Bocage</term>
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/39741613/#Girard_de_Rialle,_Julien,_1841-1904">Girard de Rialle, Julien, 1841-1904</term>
<term>A. O'Neill</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="geonames" n="places">
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/886841/mashonaland-west-province.html">Mashonaland</term>
<term target="http://www.geonames.org/2264397/portuguese-republic.html">Portugal</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2271989/algarve.html">Algarve</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2988507/paris.html">Paris, France</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/924329/lake-nyasa.html">Lake Nyassa</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2420477/republic-of-guinea.html">Guinea</term>
<term>River Casamance</term>
<term>River San Domingo de Cacheu</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2419799/rio-inxanche.html">River Cajet</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2414451/iles-tristao.html">Tristão</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2422466/rio-compony.html">Rio Componi</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2374293/rio-cacine.html">Rio Cassini</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2420896/fouta-djallon.html">Fouta-Djallon</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2260494/republic-of-the-congo.html">Congo</term>
<term>Chamba Point</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/1043442/lago-luali.html">Luali</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2258362/loeme.html">Loema</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2258375/loango.html">Loango</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/211032/lubinda-mwenge.html">Lubinda</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2241880/shiloango.html">Chiloango</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/3351879/republic-of-angola.html">Angola</term>
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/1036973/republic-of-mozambique.html">Mozambique</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>  
</textClass>


</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-09" who="#phh">encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="x"/>
<div2>
<head>Correspondence respecting Action of Portugal in Mashonaland
and in the Districts of the Shiré and Lake Nyassa</head>
<ab>No. 1</ab>
<ab><hi rend="italic">Mr. Petre to the Marquis of Salisbury.—(Received July 5.)</hi></ab>
<ab>(Extract.)
<hi rend="italic">Lisbon, June 22, 1887.</hi></ab>
<p>I HAVE the honour to transmit to your Lordship the text, in French, of the Treaty signed at Paris on the 12th May, 1886.</p>
<ab>Inclosure in No. 1.</ab>
<ab><hi rend="italic">Convention relating to the Delimitation of the French and Portuguese Possessions in
West Africa.—Signed at Paris, May 12, 1886</hi></ab>
</div2>
<div2>
<ab>(Translation.)</ab>
<p>HIS Majesty the King of Portugal and Algarves, and the President of the French
Republic, animated by the desire to draw more closely, through good neighbourly relations and perfect harmony, the bonds of friendship which exist between the two countries, have determined to draw up, for this purpose, a special Convention to arrange the delimitation of their respective possessions in West Africa, and have named the following as their Plenipotentiaries;</p>
<p>His Majesty the King of Portugal and Algarves, M. João d’Andrade Corvo,
Councillor of State, Vice-President of the Chamber of Peers, Grand Cross of the Order of
St. James, Grand Cross of the Legion of Honour, his Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
Plenipotentiary to the French Republic, &amp;c., and M. Carlos Roma du Bocage, Deputy
Captain of Engineers on the Staff, Honorary Aide-de-camp and Military Attaché at
the Legation at the Court of His Majesty the Emperor of Germany and King of Prussia,
Chevalier of the Order of St. James, Officer of the Legion of Honour, &amp;c.;</p>
<p>The President of the French Republic, M. Girard de Rialle, Minister Plenipotentiary,
Chief of the Department of the Archives in the Ministry for Foreign Affairs, Chevalier of
the Legion of Honour, and Captain O’Neill, of the Navy, Commander of the Legion of
Honour, &amp;c.;</p>
<p>Who, after declaration of their full powers, which were found to be in good and due
form, agreed to the following Articles</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE I.</head>
<p>In Guinea, the frontier which shall separate the Portuguese from the French
possessions, will follow, in accordance with the tracing upon Map I, which is annexed to
the present Convention.</p>
<p>In the north, a line which, starting from Cape Roxo, will keep as far as the nature
of the ground will permit, at an equal distance from the Rivers Casamance (Casamansa)
and San Domingo de Cacheu (São Domingos de Cacheu) to the point of intersection of
17° 30' longitude west of Paris with the parallel 12° 40' of north latitude, between this
point and the 16° of longitude west of Paris the frontier shall be merged in the parallel
12° 40' of north latitude.</p>
<p>In the east, the frontier will follow the meridian of 16° west from the 12° 40' parallel
of north latitude to the 11° 40' parallel north latitude.</p>
<p>In the south, the frontier will follow a line starting from the mouth of the River
Cajet, which lies between the Island of Catack (which will belong to Portugal) and the
Island of Tristão (which will belong to France), and keeping, as far as the nature of the
land permits, at an equal distance between the Rio Componi (Tabati) and the Rio Cassini,
then between the northern branch of the Rio Componi (Tabati) and at first the southern
branch of the Rio Cassini (tributary of the Kacondo), afterwards the Rio Grande, until it
reaches the point where the 16th meridian of west longitude cuts the parallel 11° 40' of
north latitude.</p>
<p>Portugal will possess all the islands included between the meridian of Gape Roxo, the coast, and the southern boundary formed by &amp; line following the thalweg of the River
Cajet, and afterwards turning towards the south*west across the Passe des Pilots, where it
breaches 10° 40' north latitude, and follows it as far as the meridian of Cape Roxo.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE II.</head>
<p>His Majesty the King of Portugal and Algarves recognizes the French Protectorate
over the territories of Fouta-DJallon, such as it was established by the Treaties concluded
in 1881 between the Government of the French Republic and the Almamys of Fouta-Djalion.</p>
<p>The Government of the French Republic, on its side, binds itself not to attempt to
exercise influence within the limits assigned to Portuguese Guinea by Article I of the
present Convention. They further bind themselves not to modify the treatment which has
always been extended to Portuguese subjects by the Almamys of Fouta-Djallon.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE III.</head>
<p>In the region of the Congo, the frontier of the Portuguese and French possessions
will fellow in accordance with the tracing on Map II, annexed to the present Convention,
a line which, starting from the Chamba Point, situated at the confluence of the Loema or
Louisa Loango and the Lubinda, will keep, as far as the nature of the land permits, at an
equal distance from the two rivers, and-from the northernmost source of the River Luali
will follow the crest line which separates the basins of the Ix)ema or Louisa Loango and the Ghiloango as far as 10° 30' of longitude east of Paris, when it is merged in this meridian as far as its meeting with the Chiloango, which at this point serves as the frontier between the Portuguese possessions and the Congo Free State.</p>
<p>Each of the High Contracting Parties binds itself not to raise at Chamba Point any
works of a nature to impede navigation. In the estuary comprised between Chamba Point
and the sea the thalweg will serve as political line of demarcation between the possessions of the High Contracting Parties.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE IV.</head>
<p>The Government of the French Republic recognizes the right of His Most Faithful
Majesty to exercise his sovereign and civilizing influence in the territories which separate
the Portuguese possessions of Angola and Mozambique; reserving rights already acquired
by other Powers, and binds itself on its side to abstain from all occupation there.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE V.</head>
<p>Portaguese subjects in the French possessions on the West Coast of Africa and
French citizens in the Portuguese possessions on the same coast shall be respectively
treated on a footing of equality with the citizens and subjects of the other Contracting
Power in all matters concerning the protection of life and property.
Each of the High Contracting Parties shall enjoy within the said possessions the
treatment of the most favoured nation as regards navigation and commerce.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE VI.</head>
<p>The State domains of each of the High Contracting Powers in the mutually ceded
territories shall be the subject of exchanges and compensations.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE VII.</head>
<p>A Commission will be appointed to determine on the spot the definitive position of the
lines of demarcation laid down in Articles I and III of the present Convention, and the
members compering it will be selected in the following manner:—</p>
<p>His Most Faithful Majesty and the President of the French Republic will each name
two Commissioners.</p>
<p>These Commissioners will meet at the place ultimately decided on by common
agreement by the High Contracting Parties, and as soon as possible after the exchange of
ratifications of the present Convention.</p>
<p>In case of disagreement, the said Commissioners shall refer the matter to the High
Contracting Parties.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<head>ARTICLE VIII.</head>
<p>The present Convention shall be ratified, and the ratifications exchanged as soon as
possible at Lisbon.</p>
<p>In faith thereof, the respective Commissioners signed the present Convention and
affixed their seals.</p>
<ab>Paris, May 12, 1886.</ab>
</div2>
<div2 type="signatures">
<signed>(L.S.) JOAO DF. ANDRADE CORVO.</signed>
<signed>(L.S.) CARLOS ROMA DU BOCAGE.</signed>
<signed>(L.S.) J. GIRARD DE RIALLE.</signed>
<signed>(L.S.) A. O’NEILL.</signed>
</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>