<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ardhi.treaty.00005">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Sierra Leone Treaty of 1807</title>
<principal n="Muchiri, Nganga">Nganga Muchiri</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Howells, Phillip H." xml:id="phh">Phillip H. Howells</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2020</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">ardhi.treaty.00005</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Sierra Leone Treaty of 1807 (July 10)</title>
<title level="m">The African-British Long Eighteenth Century</title>
<publisher></publisher>
<biblScope></biblScope>
<date when="2009">2009</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>  
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Treaty</term>
</keywords>     
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term key="https://viaf.org/viaf/49264990/">George III, King of Great Britain, 1738-1820</term>
</keywords>
<keywords n="treatydate">
<term>1807</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="geonames" n="places">
<term key="http://www.geonames.org/2403846">Sierra Leone</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/maps/wikipedia_8.5715_-13.0397.html">Bunce Island</term>
<term>Robiss</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/2295671/salt-town.html">Salt Town</term>
<term>Ro-Cupra</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ships">
<term/>
</keywords>   
</textClass>

<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000033">
<persName>Firama</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000034">
<persName>Tom</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000011">
<persName>George III, King of England</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000035">
<persName>Domingo</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000036">
<persName>Smith, A.</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000037">
<persName>McCauley, Alexr</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000038">
<persName>Firama, Banna</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000039">
<persName>McCauley, William</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000040">
<persName>Thorpe, John</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000041">
<persName>Wilson, John McCauley</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000042">
<persName>Edmund, David, Jr.</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000043">
<persName>Caulker, George S.</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="per.0000044">
<persName>Shaw, Charles</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2020-09" who="#phh">encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="ardhi.treaty.00005.001"/>
<div2>
<head>SIERRA LEONE TREATY OF 1807 (JULY 10)</head>
<head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">Treaty of capitulation between the Governor of
Sierra Leone and King Firama and King Tom</hi></head>
<ab><hi rend="italic">(Courtesy of British National Archives, Kew Gardens, England)</hi></ab>
<p>Treaty of peace and alliance between the Governor of the Colony of Sierra
Leone, for the Sierra Leone Company, on the one part, and King Firama and
King Tom, with their Princes and Headmen, on the other part.</p>
</div2>
<fw><hi rend="italic">Appendix of Treaties</hi>                                             169</fw>
<pb/>
<div2 type="article">
<p>1.   It is agreed that there shall henceforth be peace and friendship between the
British Colony of Sierra Leone and King Firama and King Tom, and all the
Princes, Headmen, and people subject.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="article">
<p>2.  King Firama and King Tom, with the consent of all the Headmen at this time
assembled, do hereby surrender to His Majesty the King of Great Britain,
for the use and benefit of the Sierra Leone Company, all the right, power,
and possession of every sort and kind in the peninsula of Sierra Leone and
its dependencies which they or either of them formerly had to the westward
of the Colony of Sierra Leone or any part thereof.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="article">
<p>3.   It is, nevertheless, agreed that the claim of the proprietors of Bance Island to
the possession of Cape Sierra Leone and the adjacent land, shall not be altered 
or affected by this Treaty; neither shall the claims of any other person
or persons to the same or any part thereof be affected or altered by it; but all
such claims shall remain the same as if this Treaty never had been made.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="article">
<p>4.   No native town shall be built nearer to the Colony than Robiss, except
Robiss, Salt Town, and Ro-Cupra; the land between Robin and Ro-Cupra
shall be left to the people of those places for their luggars; and in consideration 
of the permission thus given to rebuild Ro-Cupra, The Governor of
Sierra Leone shall have the right to make what use he thinks proper of Sig.
Domingo's point and the land adjacent thereto, he engaging to make a reasonable 
compensation to Sig. Domingo for the same.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="article">
<p>5.  The customary payment of one hundred bars to King Firama, as agreed
upon between him and the Governor of Sierra Leone on the 7 March 1794,
shall continue to be paid to him.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="article">
<p>6.  The Governor of Sierra Leone engages that the usual customs for watering
in St. George's Bay shall be collected regularly and paid to King Firama
and his successors, or to such person as he or they may appoint to receive
the same.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="article">
<p>7.  And to prevent disputes it is hereby acknowledged that the duties payable
for water are fifteen bars (each bar being of the full value of three shillings
and four pence sterling, if paid in goods or specie) for every trading vessel
that takes water, whether it takes little or much except crafts belonging to
traders residing on the Coast of Africa, and vessels of any description belonging 
to the Sierra Leone Company, or to the colonists of Sierra Leone,
or to the proprietor of Bance Island. And further, that no vessel ought to pay
for water more than once in one voyage, unless that voyage continue more
than a twelvemonth.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="article">
<p>8.  If any dispute shall arise concerning the boundary between the Colony and
Robiss and Ro-Cupra, the Governor of Sierra Leone and the Headmen of
Robiss and Ro-Cupra shall meet and settle it in a friendly way.</p>
</div2>
<div2>
<p>Done at Robiss this tenth day of July, in the forty-seventh year of the reign
of our sovereign Lord George the Third, of the United Kingdom of Great

<pb facs="ardhi.treaty.00005.002"/>
<fw>170                                        <hi rend="italic">Appendix of Treaties</hi></fw>
Britain and Ireland King, and in the year of our Lord one thousand eight
hundred and seven.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="signatures">
<signed>A. Smith</signed>
<signed>Alexr McCaulay</signed>
<signed>King Firama
(X mark)</signed>
<signed>King Tom
(X mark)</signed>
<signed>King Banna Firama
(X mark)</signed>
<signed>London
In presence of—
William McCaulay
John Thorpe
John McCaulay Wilson
David Edmund, junr
George S. Caulker
Charles Shaw</signed>
</div2>



<pb facs="ardhi.treaty.00005.003"/>


</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>
