<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ardhi.treaty.00029">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Mozambique Order December 1890</title>
<principal n="Muchiri, Nganga">Nganga Muchiri</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Howells, Phillip H." xml:id="phh">Phillip H. Howells</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2021</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">ardhi.treaty.00029</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Mozambique Order December 1890</title>
<title level="m"></title>
<publisher></publisher>
<biblScope></biblScope>
<date when="1890">1890</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>  
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Treaty</term>
</keywords>     
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/30336432/#Fernando_II.,_Rei_de_Portugal_1816-1885">Fernando II de Portugal</term>
<term>Joaquin Machado</term>
</keywords>
<keywords n="treatydate">
<term>1890</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="geonames" n="places">
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1036973/republic-of-mozambique.html">Mozambique</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1040649/maputo-province.html">Lourenço Marques</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/3351879/republic-of-angola.html">Angola</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/3374766/republic-of-cabo-verde.html">Cape Verde</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/972062/kwazulu-natal.html">Natal</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/3367577/cape-of-good-hope.html">Cape of Good Hope</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="pers.0000115">
<persName>Joaquin Machado</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-12" who="#phh">encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="x"/>
<div2>
<ab><hi rend="italic">Extract from the "Official Bulletin" of the Province of Mozambique of December 27,</hi> 1890.</ab>
<ab><hi rend="italic">Portaria</hi></ab>
<p>WHEREAS it is desirable to give facilities to traders passing from place to place
in this province, and, as far as possible to save them all delay and formalities;</p>
<p>Whereas under the Decree, having force of law, dated the 10th November, 1887,
persons going to the port of Lourenço Marques are no longer required to take out
passports;</p>
<p>Whereas passports have long ago been abolished in the Provinces of Angola and
Cape Verde, so far as concerns passage from one place to another in the province, and
whereas experience has shown that no inconvenience to good order and public security
has arisen therefrom, notwithstanding that Angola has a penal Settlement like Mozambique;</p>
<p>Whereas, in the Table of stamp duties for the provinces beyond the seas, the fees
for passports for the interior were abolished on the understanding that this measure
would cause no loss to the public Treasury ;</p>
<p>Whereas the Government Council has been consulted, and whereas I am authorized
thereto by the Government of His Majesty, in virtue of the powers conferred upon me
by paragraph 2 of Article 15 of the First Additional Act to the Constitutional Charter
of Mozambique;</p>
<ab>I think proper to order as follows:—</ab>
<p>1. All free persons, in the full enjoyment of their civil and political rights, whether
Portuguese subjects or foreigners, may pass from one port to another within the
the province, or from any point of the coast to the interior of the province, in case
they are going to regions outside Portuguese territory, without the necessity of taking
out passports.</p>
<p>2. This order does not invalidate the provisions of the Royal Decrees of the 3rd
February, 1875, and of the 18th July, 1876, respecting the emigration of natives to the
Colonies of Natal and of the Cape of Good Hope in case they intend embarking at
Lourenço Marques, nor the Regulations or other provincial provisions on the above
subject and on the clandestine emigration of natives.</p>
<p>Let the authorities and others concerned obey this order and act according to it.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="signatures">
<signed>(Signed) J. MACHADO, <hi rend="italic">Governor-General</hi>.</signed>
</div2>
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>