<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ardhi.treaty.00024">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Treaty with Muzila, 1861.</title>
<principal n="Muchiri, Nganga">Nganga Muchiri</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Howells, Phillip H." xml:id="phh">Phillip H. Howells</name>

</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2021</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">ardhi.treaty.00024</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to To Enter Africa from America, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="a">Treaty with Muzila, 1861.</title>
<title level="m"></title>
<publisher></publisher>
<biblScope></biblScope>
<date when="1861">1861</date>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term/>
</keywords>  
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Treaty</term>
</keywords>     
<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term>Onofre Lourenço de Andrada</term>
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/121595990/#Lu%C3%ADs_I_de_Portugal_Rei_de_Portugal_e_Algarves_(1861%E2%80%931889)">Luís I, King of Portugal, 1838-1889</term>
<term>Chieftain Muzila</term>
<term key="http://viaf.org/viaf/232843140/#Neves,_Diocleciano_Fernandes_das">Diocleciano Fernandes das Neves</term>
<term>Ignacio José de Paiva Raposo</term>
<term>José de Sequeira Campello</term>
<term>Onofre de Paiva de Andrada</term>
</keywords>
<keywords n="treatydate">
<term>1861</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="geonames" n="places">
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/7350239/gazaland-school.html">Gazaland</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1026804/sofala-province.html">Sofala</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1040947/manica-province.html">Manica</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1040649/maputo-province.html">Lourenço Marques</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/2264397/portuguese-republic.html">Portugal</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/7873980/moamba-district.html">Moamba</term>
<term>Cherinha</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1090080/manhica.html">Manhica</term>
<term>Jujote</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1045278/komati.html">Incomati River</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1045110/inhambane-province.html">Inhambane</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/6942134/bazaruto-archipelago.html">Bazaruto</term>
<term>Senna</term>
<term key="https://www.geonames.org/1026014/tete.html">Tete</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>  
</textClass>
<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="pers.0000104">
<persName>Diocleciano Fernandes das Neves</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="pers.0000105">
<persName>Ignacio José de Paiva Raposo</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="pers.0000106">
<persName>José de Sequeira Campello</persName>
</person>
<person role="signatory" xml:id="pers.0000107">
<persName>Onofre de Paiva de Andrada</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>

</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-11" who="#phh">encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 xml:lang="en" type="document">

<pb facs="x"/>
<div2>
<ab>GAZALAND-SOFALA AND MANICA.</ab>
<p><hi rend="italic">Treaty with Muzila, December</hi> 2,1861.</p>
<p>TERMS proposed by the Governor of the Lourenço Marques district. Lieutenant-Colonel 
of the Portuguese army, Onofre Loureuço de Andrada, to the Chieftain
Muzila, for the concession of assistance requested by him from this Government: the
former acting for His Most Faithful Majesty the King of Portugal, and the latter in
his own name and that of his successors: terms accepted by the said Chieftain Muzila
without constraint or opposition, and in the presence of the under-named witnesses:—</p>
<p>1. The Chieftain Muzila, after taking oath according to his custom and practice,
remains a tributary Chieftain and subject of the Portuguese Crown, as well as all his
subordinates, obeying all orders issued from this Government of Loureço Marques.</p>
<p>2. The said Chieftain will impose on all his subordinates the utmost respect and
esteem towards all "molungos” (Portuguese) in transit through his dominions; and
whenever there may he a breach of this rigorous duty, he, Muzila, shall immediately
order the culprit to he severely punished, as an example—the privileges of this clause
are extended to all negroes from the dominions of the Crown who may visit Muzila’s
territories in public or in private service, whether by order of the Government or of
any inhabitant of the country.</p>
<p>3. The commerce and chase of all animals will be free to all. Portuguese who may
go or send to that effect to the dominions of the said Chieftain Muzila, and, far from
hindering them, he will protect them to the extent of his power.</p>
<p>4. The Chieftain Muzila will permit the construction in his own dominions of all
fortifications that the Portuguese Government may consider necessary for the defence
and security of the same; and also, all small or large plantations that the said
Government, or any private person of Portuguese nationalily, may think proper to
lay or have laid in territories most to the latter’s convenience; and not only the said
Muzila will not oppose them, but will even direct their choice to the most productive
soil if so asked.</p>
<p>5. The Portuguese flag shall be hoisted in the village where the said Chieftain
Muzila may reside, and he shall not declare war with any people without previously
informing this Government his motives for so acting, except it be to defend himself
from any act of aggression made in his territory; and, in this case also and immediately 
thereafter, he must inform the Government of Lourenço Marques of the fact.</p>
<p>6. The territories of Moamba, Cherinha, Manhica, and Jujote, on this side of the
Incomati River, are, from this day, subjected and tributary to the Portuguese Crown,
and none else will have a right to tribute them.</p>
<p>7. All “ milando ” (Kaffir dialect) or controversy between white or negro inhabitants 
of the Crown dominions and Muzila’s subordinates will be judged at this fortress
in the Governor’s presence, or of any person by him appointed.</p>
<p>8. The Chieftain Muzila, as soon as he entersinto possession of his dominions, will
return to this fortress all the refugee negro slaves, and will so continue to do every
time any slave belonging to the said fortress seeks a shelter in his territories.</p>
<p>9. The CMeftain Muzila will understand that the respect and esteem imposed by
Article 2 are extensive to all “molungos” (Portuguese) of Inhambane, Sofala, Bazaruto, 
Manica, Senna, and Tete, all brethren to the Portuguese of Lourenço Marques.</p>
<p>10. The Portuguese Government is bound to help the said Chieftain Muzila and
his successors, wheneverso required, with armed forces, against all aggression made on
territories occupied by them, so long as the said Chieftain scrupulously complies with
the duties announced in the foregoing Articles.</p>
<p>11. The Portuguese Government undertakes the construction of a house made of
masonry (as is in use in this fortress) for the private use of the said Chieftain Muzila
and-successors, and at the village by him chosen for his residence.</p>
<p>12. The Portuguese Government undertakes to defray all expenses of education im
Portuguese institutionsfor two or more sons of the CMeftain Muzfla, that the same may
desire to be so-educated.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="signatures">
<signed>(Signed) DIOCLECIANO FERNANDES DAS NEVES.</signed>
<signed>IGNACIO JOSÉ DE PAIVA RAPOSO.</signed>
<signed>JOSE PE SEQUEIRA CAMPELLO, <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant
in charge of the Despatch</hi>.</signed>
<signed>ONOFRE DE PAIVA DE ANDRADA.</signed>
<ab><hi rend="italic">Government Quarters of Lourenço Morgues,
December 2,</hi> 1861.</ab>
</div2>
</div1>

</body>
</text>

</TEI>